Boker tov (בוקר טוב). Boker tov Today's daf (דף) daf is Lamed
(למד). Lamed We're in the middle of a very explanation of a
very rich Mishnah (משנה). Mishnah We've just dealt with the parental obligations
to children, which basically, as the Gemara (גמרא) Gemara says, are fatherly
obligations to the son. And we've done the mitzvos (מצוות) mitzvos of
bris milah (ברית מילה), bris milah pidyon haben (פדיון הבן), pidyon haben
and Talmud Torah (תלמוד תורה). Talmud Torah And we're going to be
continuing today, particularly with a focus in Talmud Torah (תלמוד תורה), Talmud
Torah but moving on to other issues as well. So let's take
a look at what the Gemara (גמרא) Gemara says on Kaf Tet
Amud Bet (כט עמוד ב). Kaf Tet Amud Bet I mean, the
daf (דף) daf is daf Lamed (דף למד), daf Lamed and we're
at Kaf Tet Amud Bet (כט עמוד ב), Kaf Tet Amud Bet
and we are up to Tanu Rabbanan (תנו רבנן). Tanu Rabbanan It
is about 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11 lines
down in the wide lines, last word on the line before an
asterisk. Tanu Rabbanan (תנו רבנן): Tanu Rabbanan lilmod Torah v'lisa isha (ללמוד
תורה ולישא אשה). lilmod Torah v'lisa isha Let's say it is between
learning Torah (תורה) Torah and getting married. Now, we're no longer about
the parental
obligation. We're just about questions of priority, similar to the way we
raised the question about: are you podeh (פודה) podeh yourself first or
your son first? Do you teach yourself Torah (תורה) Torah first or
your son Torah (תורה) Torah first? Do you first oleh l'regel (עולה
לרגל) oleh l'regel or are you first pidyon haben (פדיון הבן)? pidyon
haben So here's the question about marriage versus Talmud Torah (תלמוד תורה).
Talmud Torah Okay, so learning Torah (תורה) Torah and getting married. And
actually, interestingly, next on the Mishnah (משנה) Mishnah is the obligation is
to marry off your sons. But okay, as to between those two,
you have to choose: what am I going to do, you know,
as a young man? Should I prioritize getting married or should I
prioritize learning Torah (תורה)? Torah Yilmod Torah v'achar kach yisa isha (ילמוד
תורה ואחר כך ישא אשה). yilmod Torah v'achar kach yisa isha First
learn Torah (תורה) Torah and then get married. Okay, presumably because once
you get married, as the Gemara (גמרא) Gemara is going to say,
you're going to have a lot of other obligations and you won't
have your time and efforts being able to focus on your Torah
(תורה) Torah learning. V'im iy efshar lo b'lo isha (ואם אי אפשר
לו בלא אשה), V'im iy efshar lo b'lo isha but if it
is not possible for you to live without a wife, meaning, again,
obviously the Gemara (גמרא) Gemara is speaking totally to men, so you
know, you could sort of say, you know, you just need the
companionship, you know, or for emotional reasons. But as we're going to
see clearly also, the Gemara (גמרא) Gemara is going to be talking
about its concern about sexual thoughts. Not necessarily clear that that's what
it's referring to here. Anyway, for whatever reason, a man feels that
he needs to get married, fine, then yisa isha v'achar yilmod Torah
(ישא אשה ואחר כך ילמוד תורה). yisa isha v'achar yilmod Torah It's
not a strict hierarchy. If you need to, you can get married
first, but ideally you should first spend your time learning because that
will allow you to focus your energies. Now what also should be
mentioned
is
that obviously implicit in this statement is the sense of an ongoing
responsibility to learn. And you know, the Gemara (גמרא) Gemara said before
a very strange statement that your father's obligated to teach the son;
if the father didn't teach the son, then the son has to
teach himself. Which indicates not this lifelong obligation of Talmud Torah (תלמוד
תורה), Talmud Torah indicates like a certain amount of a foundational education,
right? And now, but of course we know that the whole ethos
of the rabbis is like, you know, you should always be learning
Torah (תורה). Torah Vehagita bo yomam valailah (והגית בו יומם ולילה). vehagita
bo yomam valailah Actually, a pasuk (פסוק) pasuk that has not been
quoted until now, right? V'shinantam l'vanecha (ושננתם לבניך) v'shinantam l'vanecha so that's
teach your children. But then it's v'dibarta bam b'shivtecha b'vetecha u'v'lechtecha vaderech
(ודברת בם בשבתך בביתך ובלכתך בדרך) v'dibarta bam b'shivtecha b'vetecha u'v'lechtecha vaderech
right? the constant learning of Torah (תורה). Torah So that hasn't really
been fully explicated halachically, you know, the nature of that obligation as
opposed to the nature of the parental obligation to educate. But clearly
that's assumed here: you should be learning as much as possible, growing
as much as possible in your Torah (תורה). Torah So that should
come first. But if for either because of sexual thoughts or other
reasons you need to get married first, then okay, you can get
married first. If you have to do that for yourself, then you
do that for yourself. Yes, Charlie.
"Well, today there is a third reason, which is the father-in-law who
pays the expenses while the son-in-law is learning Torah (תורה)."
Torah All right, there you go. That could be a reason why
you need to get married in order to learn Torah (תורה). Torah
Okay, so the Gemara (גמרא) Gemara says like this. Now, Amar Rav
Yehuda Amar Shmuel (אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל): Amar Rav Yehuda Amar
Shmuel halachah (הלכה), halachah the halachah (הלכה) halachah is nosei isha v'achar
yilmod Torah (נושא אשה ואחר כך ילמוד תורה) nosei isha v'achar yilmod
Torah opposite of what the Gemara (גמרא) Gemara said before, opposite of
the Beraita (ברייתא). Beraita He's saying, 'No, actually first get married and
then learn Torah (תורה).' Torah Rabbi Yochanan (רבי יוחנן) Rabbi Yochanan so
it's interesting, how is Shmuel (שמואל) Shmuel paskening (פוסקן) paskening against the
Beraita (ברייתא)? Beraita I'll discuss that in a minute. Rabbi Yochanan amar
(רבי יוחנן אמר) Rabbi Yochanan amar Rabbi Yochanan (רבי יוחנן) Rabbi Yochanan
goes back to the Beraita (ברייתא) Beraita and he says, 'Reichaim b'tzavaro
v'yaasok baTorah (ריחים בצוארו ויעסוק בתורה)? Reichaim b'tzavaro v'yaasok baTorah You have
a millstone around your neck and you think you can learn Torah
(תורה)?' Torah Once you have the weight of the ol parnassah (עול
פרנסה), ol parnassah right, the yoke of family responsibilities and making a
living, when is going to be your time to learn Torah (תורה)?
Torah So therefore clearly no, you have to prioritize Torah (תורה) Torah
first, marriage later. V'lo pligi (ולא פליגי) V'lo pligi and they don't
really debate. Ha lan v'ha lahu (הא לן והא להו). ha lan
v'ha lahu That's for them, this is for us. Now, Rashi (רש"י)
Rashi says, and Rashi (רש"י) Rashi is no question pshat (פשט), pshat
that ha lan (הא לן) ha lan is Rabbi Yochanan (רבי יוחנן)
Rabbi Yochanan is talking to bnei Eretz Yisrael (בני ארץ ישראל) bnei
Eretz Yisrael and he says you learn you learn Torah (תורה) Torah
first. And Shmuel (שמואל) Shmuel is talking to bnei Bavel (בני בבל)
bnei Bavel and he says you get married first. What's the difference?
The difference is it's clear from many Gemaras (גמרות) Gemaras that in
Bavel (בבל) Bavel they would leave home and go to Eretz Yisrael
(ארץ ישראל) Eretz Yisrael to study Torah (תורה). Torah And basically, actually,
they would leave home and they would not attend to their to
their obligations to their wives and children. If people remember the beginning
of Gittin (גיטין) Gittin which we learned not so long ago, right,
it tells the story that who was it, was it Rabbi Avahu
(רבי אבהו) Rabbi Avahu or not Rabbi Abbahu (רבי אבהו), Rabbi Abbahu
Rav Chisda (רב חסדא)? Rav Chisda No, Rabbi Chiya bar Abba (רבי
חייא בר אבא) Rabbi Chiya bar Abba who was in Eretz Yisrael
(ארץ ישראל) Eretz Yisrael wrote to people who were living in Bavel
(בבל) Bavel who said, 'Those people that leave Bavel (בבל) Bavel and
come here to learn.' תורה, Torah, they are fulfilling the verse ויתנו
את הילד בזונה ואת הילדה מכרו ביין. vayitnu et hayeled b'zonah v'et
hayaldam machru bayayin. I think—is that the פסוק? pasuk? Yeah, ויתנו את
הילד בזונה ואת הילדה מכרו ביין. vayitnu et hayeled b'zonah v'et hayaldam
machru bayayin. They basically turned their kids out for prostitution because they're
abandoning their family and how is their family now supposed to support
themselves? And there's a lot of evidence about this in בבל. Bavel.
And in general, what it's also related to or very relevant to
קידושין, Kiddushin, although these גמרות Gemoras I'm about to refer to come
up in I think יבמות, Yevamos, not in קידושין, Kiddushin, is how
the גמרא Gemara describes what the value of marriage is. And a
lot of the בבל Bavel sources describe that the value of marriage
is that it protects the husband from sin, from עבירה, aveira, it
allows the husband to learn תורה, Torah, it provides a wall, it
provides, you know, the wife sort of takes care of the domestic
responsibilities so the man is free to learn תורה, Torah, whereas in
ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, the value of marriage is described in much
more intrinsic value. Like, you know, a person who's not married—obviously you're
still talking about the man—is without שמחה, simcha, is without שלום, shalom,
he's not complete, you know, in a much more sense of intrinsic
value. And some of that might have to do with the fact
that בבל, Bavel, influenced by the larger Sassanian sort of culture, right,
or still following in the biblical model, still had polygamy, whereas ארץ
ישראל Eretz Yisrael at that time, following the Roman
model by the surrounding Roman culture, basically only had monogamy. Which is
why in the end, you know,
בבל Bavel culture went to ספרד Sefarad and ספרד Sefarad also Muslims,
you know, within the Muslim lands that continued with polygamy, whereas ארץ
ישראל Eretz Yisrael went into אשכנז Ashkenaz and continued from Roman to
Christian lands and that was monogamy. And that has a lot to
do with, and that's clearly evident in other places, that the ירושלמי
Yerushalmi pretty much assumes monogamy and the בבלי Bavli assumes polygamy. Anyway,
that has to do to some degree with how you think about
marriage. If marriage is only between one man and one woman, you
think about it much more in terms of like a partnership and
not in utilitarian types of ways, right? But if you have a
model of marriage—now very few people, I don't know, it was only
the wealthy men in society usually that had more than one wife—but
nevertheless, the way marriage is thought of in an area where polygamy
is present, right, is much more like it's not a partnership man
and woman. It's like I have a wife but it's more like
as a member of my household, whereas I don't even only have
one wife, and therefore that shifts an attitude. So it does seem
that in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, there's a much greater sense of:
you're married, those now that's your primary responsibility. You don't shirk those
responsibilities for anything else. תורה Torah comes after you first take care
of your primary responsibility to your wife and your kids. Whereas in
בבל, Bavel, the attitude was: no, I'm married and, but תורה Torah
trumps, I'm going to leave my wife and kids and I'm going
to go learn תורה. Torah. Okay. And therefore in ארץ ישראל, Eretz
Yisrael, since once you get married that has to be priority number
one, the answer is: you better learn your תורה Torah before you
get married. Because once you get married, ריחיים בצווארו ויעסוק בתורה? reichayim
b'tzavaro v'ya'asok batorah? Once you get married, that's your primary responsibility. So
therefore, don't get married until you've achieved a significant level of תלמוד
תורה. Talmud Torah. Whereas in בבל, Bavel, it was like: okay, so
I'll get married now and then I'll still go ahead and learn
תורה. Torah. Why not get married first? Okay, and that's the way
רש״י Rashi explains it, and you know, by getting married first you're
able to have an outlet for your sexual needs and so on.
And so you get married, you take care of that, but nevertheless
you go ahead and you still leave your wife and you spend
a lot of time learning תורה. Torah. So that's how רש״י Rashi
explains it and that seems totally פשט. pshat. תוספות Tosafot just is
too scandalized by that idea that the בבלי Bavli would seem to
endorse abandoning your wife and kids and endorse the ability for you
to not prioritize your, you know, your obligations to your family. So
תוספות Tosafot has a complicated way of rereading the גמרא. Gemara. But
it seems like רש״י Rashi is like definitely the פשט. pshat. So
it really becomes quite an interesting issue of which comes first, because
the question ultimately becomes, you know, on the one hand, recognizing the
human need to be married and particularly, as we're going to see
in a minute, the issue about sexual thoughts and the גמרא Gemara
wanting to address that from a religious perspective. And on the other
hand, the high priority of תלמוד תורה. Talmud Torah. And then the
question becomes like, can, if you are, you know, which if you're
married, are you allowed to set aside or to make second in
priority your obligations to your wife and kids? And the way at
least רש״י Rashi reads this, that's essentially the debate of בבל Bavel
and ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, which determines whether you can get married
first or have to wait to get married. Yes.
I was also wondering, you mentioned the priority of the תלמוד תורה.
Talmud Torah. So, you know, if he can do it on his
own, you know, does there, does the father's obligation end at some
point?
It seems like it's like twenty years old or... All right, we're
going to get to, we're going to get back to the father's
obligation. We're not, we're not talking about that right now. Anyway, I
did want to share, so that's a great question, as I said,
which has broader implications about prioritizing responsibility, attitude towards marriage between בבל
Bavel and ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and so on. Now, I want
to say also just a cute line that my brother who is
a... And in the מיר Mir told me, so, which is just
to tell the ישיבה yeshiva humor. Anyway, apparently there's a story that
in וואלאזשין, Volozhin, you know, when students were learning, רב חיים, Rav
Chaim, you know, רב חיים Rav Chaim of בריסק, Brisk, who was
obviously the ראש ישיבה Rosh Yeshiva of וואלאזשין, Volozhin, would like circulate
around to like listen in to the students as they were learning
בחברותא. be-chavruta. You know, so he'd go over to a בחברותא be-chavruta
and they were like in learning and he'd like put his arm
around like the guy and by listening in, of course the kids
were like terrified, right? So another ראש ישיבה Rosh Yeshiva walks by
and he says, רב חיים בצוארו ויעסוק בתורה? Rav Chaim b'tzavaro ve-yassek
b'Torah?
Okay, so that's only you have to be very much of an
insider to get that joke. Yes.
No, we did that already.
Yeah, I have a very simple question from what רש"י Rashi says
here on this section, about go to ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and
learn משניות. Mishnayot. Like, is there anything to say about that, like
how, what'd he get that from? Like the איגרת? Iggeret? Like how
would he know what the and there's no thought about תוספתא? Tosefta?
Yeah, I don't know why he mentions,
yeah, it's so striking, right? Like really, they go just to learn
the משנה? Mishna?
Yeah, well maybe he said because רב יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is the
first generation אמורא, Amora, so he assumes that. But of course, but
even in the period of the תנאים, Tanaim, we assume that there
was still the debate and analysis or whatever, just wasn't recorded. But
I was wondering about that too. He might say because רב יוחנן,
Rabbi Yochanan, right, I thought maybe because רב יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan was
the first generation אמורא. Amora. Okay, let's continue. Now because we're dealing
with this, so we really were talking about תלמוד תורה, Talmud Torah,
but you know, but maybe because we're somewhat situated in מסכת קידושין,
Masechet Kiddushin, it'd be because, you know, this is as we see
till today, the ongoing challenge. If you make תורה, Torah, which is
this all-consuming response, you know, sort of מצוה, mitzvah, which we have
not explained that that's true about it, right? We started with it
just as an obligation of like primary education of father to child,
son. But anyway, if it's this all-consuming מצוה, mitzvah, you know, and
then how does that play out in terms of a man's responsibility
to his family, right? And that's like, you know, that's still today,
like in כולל Kollel and all these places where the guys sit
and they spend the whole time and they're not, you know, and
they're not sort of being taking parental responsibility so much
and raising and earning the money, etc. And there've been different attitudes.
רמב"ם, Rambam, on the other hand, writes very sharply in פירוש משניות
Peirush Mishnayot and elsewhere, you know, on the משנה Mishna in פרקי
אבות Pirkei Avot about אל תעשה קרדום לחפור בו, al ta'aseh kardom
lachpor bo, don't make the תורה Torah a shovel to dig with
it. He says like people that go ahead and think that because
they're learning תורה, Torah, they can have the ציבור tzibbur support them,
you know, he says it's like horrific and like, and that if
you look in the גמרא, Gemara, everybody had a פרנסה, parnassa, and
you can't be supported by the community. Now that's in terms of
support by the community. Okay, you know what you have nowadays, right,
sometimes you have the father-in-law supporting, but often you have the wives
going out and supporting, which is exactly the dynamic in the גמרא,
Gemara, right? And that's exactly the question, like, and that seemed to
have been a major issue between בבל Bavel and ארץ ישראל, Eretz
Yisrael, whether that was a legitimate trade-off for the sake of תלמוד
תורה, Talmud Torah, or your family obligations come first. Okay, so now
within that context of תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah and marriage, we have
the גמרא Gemara continuing, or the general issue about marriage, maybe because
of getting married for the יצר הרע yetzer hara reasons, well we
haven't said that, but we said if you need to get married.
So let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. So משתבח ליה
רב חסדא לרב הונא. mishtabbach lei Rav Chisda l'Rav Huna. So רב
חסדא Rav Chisda was praising, was talking to רב הונא Rav Huna
and singing the praises of רב המנונא, Rav Hamnuna, about רב המנונא.
Rav Hamnuna. אדם גדול הוא. adam gadol hu. Oh, this רב המנונא,
Rav Hamnuna, you won't believe it, he's such a huge תלמיד חכם.
talmid chacham. אמר ליה, amar lei, so רב הונא Rav Huna said
to רב חסדא, Rav Chisda, כי אתי לגבך, ki yatei l'gabbach, next
time he happens by you, אייתי ליה לידי, aityei l'yadi, bring him,
bring him to me, I'd like to see him. So כי אתא,
ki ata, so he brought him to him, so רב הונא Rav
Huna was presented to רב המנונא... Rav Hamnuna... רב המנונא Rav Hamnuna
was presented to רב הונא. Rav Huna. חזיה, chazei, so רב הונא
Rav Huna saw him, דלא פריס סודרא, de-lo parus sudra, he wasn't
wearing a like a type of a scarf around his head, which
was a turban, which was something that was worn by married men.
So אמר ליה, amar lei, מאי טעמא לא פריסת סודרא? mai ta'ama
lo parist sudra? Why are you not wearing this scarf? אמר ליה,
amar lei, דלא נסיבנא, de-lo nessivna, because I'm not married. אהדרינהו לאפיה
מיניה, ahadrinhu l'appei mineih, he turned his face away from him, he
refused to look at him. אמר ליה, amar lei, חזי, chazi, pay
attention, דלא חזית לאפי, de-lo chazit le-happeia, I won't see you
or you won't see my face, עד דנסבת, ad nessivta, until you
get married. I refuse to look at you until you get married.
Okay, now why was he so strict? רב הונא לטעמיה, Rav Huna
l'ta'ameih, רב הונא's Rav Huna going to his reasoning, דאמר, de-amar, who
said, בן עשרים שנה ולא נשא אשה, ben esrim shana ve-lo nasa
isha, if a man is twenty years old and has not yet
gotten married, כל ימיו בעבירה, kol yamav ba-aveira, all of his days
are in sin. עבירה סלקא דעתך? aveira salka da'atach? Literally he's in
sin, he's sinning? אלא אימא כל ימיו בהרהור עבירה, ella eima kol
yamav b'hirhur aveira, he's constantly besieged by sexual thoughts. אמר רבא, amar
Rava, וכן תנא דבי רבי ישמעאל, v'chen tana d'vei Rabbi Yishmael, עד
כ' שנים, ad kaf shanim, up until twenty years old, יושב הקדוש
ברוך הוא ומצפה לאדם מתי ישא
אשה, yoshev HaKadosh Baruch Hu u-metzapeh l'adam matay yissa isha, God's sort
of waiting, נו, nu, נו, nu, you're seventeen already, still not married,
eighteen, nineteen, until you're twenty, He's waiting. כיון שהגיע כ' ולא נשא,
keivan she-higia kaf ve-lo nasa, once he gets twenty and you're still
not married, אמר תיפח עצמותיו, amar tippach atzmotav,
let your bones be blasted, I can't believe you're already twenty and
not married.
Parenting model, exactly.
Exactly. אמר רב חסדא, Amar Rav Chisda, האי דעדיפנא מחבראי, hai de'adifna
mikhavray,
you know why I'm at a higher like religious level than my
colleagues? דנסיבנא בשיתסר, denasivna beshis'ar, I got married at the age of
sixteen. So therefore that satisfied all of my יצר הרע yetzer hara
outlets, you know? ואי הוי נסיבנא בארביסר, ve'i hava nasivna be'arbesar,
but if I got married at fourteen, then I would have totally
been in control of my sexual desire. הא אמינא לשטן, ha'amina lesatan,
I would have said to the שטן, satan, גירי בעינך, girei be'einecha,
arrows in your eyes. Okay now, now what again you see here
is that this is very much all ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, all
בבל אמוראים, Bavel Amora'im, and all pushing for an early age for
marriage. Why? Because of the idea of marriage as an outlet for
your sexual thoughts and desires. Okay, so very much this sort of
instrumental serving the man's needs type of an approach towards marriage, right?
Not this like intrinsic good of bringing man and woman together. And
if you're getting married at a young age, obviously you're getting married
before you're learning תורה Torah at a serious high level. So again,
very consistent, right, with what we said before. Interestingly,
רמב''ם Rambam uses this as opposed to that this is really not
a הלכה halacha in הלכות קידושין, Hilchos Kiddushin, as it were, like
in the מצוה mitzvah of getting married, this is more הלכה halacha
in like הרהורי עבירה hirhurei aveira הלכות. halachas. You know, רמב''ם Rambam
makes it part of הלכות קידושין. Hilchos Kiddushin. And if you take
a look at רמב''ם Rambam here, I'll just pull it up for
you, because now I got everything on my phone, right, רמב''ם Rambam
basically says, and רמב''ם Rambam comes up with the number seventeen somehow,
and רמב''ם Rambam says the following. You got the number seventeen means
to be
married by seventeen? What?
Yeah, basically, the רמב''ם Rambam says the following, he says, let's see,
I'll read you the רמב''ם, Rambam, רמב''ם Rambam says, האיש מצווה פריה
ורביה ולא אשה. ha'ish metzuve p'ru u'rvu ve'lo isha.
So he's talking in the context of פריה ורביה. p'ru u'rvu. ואימתי
האיש מתחייב במצוה זו? ve'ematai ha'ish mitchayev bemitzvah zo? When is a
man obligated to start having kids? Whatever, מבין שבע עשרה, miben sheva
esrei, from seventeen. רמב''ם Rambam also says that the מצוה mitzvah of
having kids is only in the context of marriage. וכיון שעברו עשרים
שנה, vekevan she'avru esrim shana, so he starts with seventeen, not clear
where he gets that from, that wasn't a number in this גמרא,
Gemara, but once you hit twenty years, which was the number in
our גמרא, Gemara, ולא נשא אשה הרי זה עובר ומבטל מצות עשה.
ve'lo nasa isha harei ze over u'mevattel mitzvas asei.
You're actively negating a positive מצוה, mitzvah, you're not מקיים, bekayem, which
is a very bizarre idea, right? Because you would think as long
as the guy's going to have kids in his life, he's not
at a point where he's מבטל, mevattel, he's only מבטל mevattel if
he passes the point of no return, right? You're maybe postponing, you're
pushing it off to a later time. The רמב''ם Rambam frames it
as no, you basically up till twenty is when, after twenty you're
considered to be מבטל mevattel the מצוה. mitzvah. אם היה עוסק בתורה
וטרוד והיה מתיירא משא אשה כדי שלא יטרח במזונותיו, im hayah osek
baTorah ve'tarud ve'haya mityarei misa isha kedei shelo yitrach bimzonosav,
but if you were learning תורה Torah and you were afraid that
getting married would take you away because of support of having to
earn a living, then הרי זה מותר להתאחר שעוסק במצוה פטור מן
המצוה. harei ze muttar lehitchaer she'osek bemitzvah patur min hamitzvah. Okay,
so he says why are you allowed to push off marriage if
you're learning תורה? Torah? עוסק במצוה פטור מן המצוה. osek bemitzvah patur
min hamitzvah. But basically, the רמב''ם Rambam introduces an idea that if
you're not married by twenty, it's like an actual ביטול bittul of
the מצות עשה. mitzvas asei. Which is strange from two perspectives. Number
one, this גמרא Gemara was only concerned about הרהורים, hirhurim, it wasn't
concerned about a ביטול מצוה. bittul mitzvah. And number two, again, what's
the model to talk about it as a ביטול מצוה bittul mitzvah
as opposed to just postponing the מצוה? mitzvah?
And it's, you know, obviously the fact is that anybody who doesn't
get married nowadays at twenty, any community that isn't pushing, you know,
its kids to get married at the age of twenty is either
effectively paskening not like the רמב''ם, Rambam, or saying that even this
concept of ביטול מצוה, bittul mitzvah, you know, doesn't exist if it's
not yet the right time. Like the right time is part of
framing right when that מצוה mitzvah is. It's very relevant also in
discussions about having kids. Because some people say that once you're married,
you can't use like birth control, you know, even if you're young
and you have plenty of time, etc. You can't use birth control
until you've had two kids because the רמב''ם Rambam says that you're
being מבטל mevattel the מצוה mitzvah if you don't, you know, take
care of it right away. The funny thing is, nobody was telling
me I was being מבטל mevattel the מצוה mitzvah until I waited
until twenty-five to get married. So now that I'm married at twenty-five,
why are you telling me I'm מבטל mevattel the מצוה mitzvah if
I'm waiting a few more years to have kids? So anyway, this
language that the רמב''ם Rambam uses that it's ביטול מצוה bittul mitzvah
of פריה ורביה p'ru u'rvu once you hit the age of twenty
is a very strange concept that the רמב''ם Rambam introduces and a
little bit hinging on this גמרא. Gemara. Yes.
And I understand that there's a concept of פת בסלו, pas besalo,
but if they're going to be leaving their family and going away
for a long time to ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, are there not
going to be any הרהורים? hirhurim?
So that's what תוספות Tosafos ask. תוספות Tosafos ask, I don't understand,
how do you think that solved the הרהורים hirhurim problem? But you
know, it does, you know, you come home for periods in between
or whatever and there is a פת בסלו, pas besalo, and you
know, it's at least better than the alternative. Yes, Charlie.
Does this whether you should hurry up to do the מצוה mitzvah
at the earliest time, that affects other things, like should we all
be davening שחרית Shacharit at dawn?
Right, so normally there's an idea of זריזים, zerizim, but the funny
thing is רמב''ם Rambam uses the phrase ביטול מצוה. bittul mitzvah. Okay,
back to the גמרא. Gemara.
That's a Talmudic phrase, ביטול מצוה? bittul mitzvah?
No. I mean, it is in other contexts. But not this time.
אמר ליה amar lei רבא לרב נתן *amar lei Rava le-Rav Natan*.
רבא *Rava* says to רב rav נתן בר אמי *Rav Natan bar
Ami*, אדידך *adideich*, for you, על צוארי דבריך *al tzavarei devareich*.
Devareich? I don't know how to pronounce that word. Devareich, your son.
משיתסר ועד עשרים ועד
עשרים ותרתין *mi-shitz'ar ve-ad esrim ve-ad esrim ve-tartin*. Have your basically your
you know arm around your son or your you know the yoke
your weight on your son's neck
from 16 to 22. Now רש"י Rashi *Rashi* has two interpretations. Either
it means to pressure him to get married or just in general
means to like try to give him like good מוסר *mussar* and
education. Of course 16 to start giving מוסר *mussar* at 16 and
you know start giving moral education seems a little late. Although רש"י
Rashi *Rashi* prefers that read to the marriage read, although the marriage
read seems much more consistent with what we just said. So anyway
we'll read it the marriage way. You know try to keep the
pressure on your son's back from the age of 16 to 22.
ואמרי לה מתמני סרי עד עשרים וארבע *ve-amre lei mi-tamne-isrei ad esrim
ve-arba*, 18 to 24. Again notice 17 isn't there. Anyway, because presumably
less than that would be too young you know to push him
to get married and more than that would actually be like at
a certain point it's too late. Like by that stage you know
it's going to be counterproductive. You know start nudging stop nudging your
kid to get married after a certain age it's not doing any
good. Okay what?
Not listening to you after a certain age.
Right. And רש"י Rashi *Rashi* also says it's based on another גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* which said that if you try to you know don't
give your son too many temptations to rebel and it's like לפני
עור *lifnei iver* of him being מבטל *mevatel* the מצוה *mitzvah* of
like כיבוד אב ואם *kibbud av va-em* or whatever. Like okay so
it's a מחלוקת תנאים *machloket tannaim* like a debate of תנאים *tannaim*.
חנוך לנער על פי דרכו *chanoch la-na'ar al pi darko*. Train the
child according to his path. רבי יהודה רבי נחמיה *Rabbi Yehuda Rabbi
Nechemiah*, חד אמר משיתסר ועד עשרים ותרתין *chad amar mi-shitz'ar ve-ad esrim
ve-tartin*, from 16 to 22. וחד אמר מתמני סרי ועד עשרים וארבע
*ve-chad amar mi-tamne-isrei ve-ad esrim ve-arba*, 18 to 24. So רש"י Rashi
*Rashi* because this says חנוך *chanoch* seems to be a general idea
of חינוך *chinuch*, so maybe we're talking more broadly about upbringing bringing
your child up. But again the context and the ages make it
sound like we're talking very much about trying to get him married
off, which by the way is the next thing that we're going
to be talking about is the father's obligation to marry off the
son. What if a daughter? Well we're going to see about that.
עד היכן חייב אדם ללמד את בנו תורה Torah, *ad hachan chayav
adam le-lammed et beno Torah*. Now back to תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah
*Talmud Torah*. That was a digression you know cause marriage is coming
up but it was the intersection. Back to תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah,
*Talmud Torah*. עד היכן חייב אדם ללמד את בנו תורה Torah *ad
hachan chayav adam le-lammed et beno Torah* and here we get back
to defining what do we mean by תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah *Talmud
Torah* and what do we mean by the father's obligation. Until what
point is a person obligated? אמר רב Rav יהודה אמר שמואל כגון
kegon זבולון בן דן *amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel kagon Zevulun ben
Dan*. Like an example would be זבולון בן דן *Zevulun ben Dan*,
certain person that they knew all very biblical names but a person
who was known at that time. שלימדו אבי אביו *she-limmdo avi aviv*,
his grandfather taught him מקרא Mikra? ומשנה *mikra u-mishnah*, תנ"ך Tanakh *Tanakh*,
משניות mishnayos *mishnayot* ותלמוד *ve-Talmud*, the Talmud, right, the analysis of it
even though there wasn't like the Vilna Shas yet. הלכות ואגדות *Halachos
ve-aggados*. He taught him everything. So basically the answer is you got
to teach your son כל התורה כולה *kol ha-Torah kullah*.
What did they mean Talmud and Halacha and Aggada?
הלכות *Halachos* are either הלכות פסוקות *halachos pesukot*. Okay and אגדות *Aggados*
are stories are אגדות *aggadot*.
And תלמוד *Talmud*
is שקלא וטריא *shakla ve-tarya*. Exactly. Okay מיתיבי *meitiv*, I'll ask you
on this. We have a ברייתא Braisah *baraita*. לימדו מקרא Mikra. אין
מלמדו משנה mishna, *limmdo mikra ein melammdo mishnah*. Once you've taught him
Tanakh you don't have an obligation to teach beyond that to teach
him even Mishnah which is a big חידוש *chiddush*. Your whole obligation
is to teach your kid Tanakh you don't even have to teach
him like basic rabbinic literature okay or you know maybe even Halacha
which is what you know anyway that's surprising. I mean certainly when
the פסוק pasuk, *pasuk* says ושיננתם לבניך ודיברת בם *ve-shinnantam le-vanecha ve-dibbartam
bam*, the Torah is talking about about מקרא Mikra *Mikra*. That's all
about you know so anyway that's all there was at the time
that that פסוק pasuk *pasuk* was given. Okay so anyway it says
of course in addition to the תורה שבעל פה Torah shebe'al peh
*Torah she-be'al peh* that was at that time. Okay good okay anyway
so it says like this. Okay where
were we? ואמר רבא מקרא Mikra, זו תורה Torah. *ve-amar
Rava Mikra zu Torah*. Not only that מקרא mikra, *Mikra* is only
תורה Torah, *Torah* it's not even נביאים וכתובים *Nevi'im u-Ketuvim*. So that's
your only obligation. So גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says כזבולון בן דן ולא
כזבולון בן דן *k-Zevulun ben Dan ve-lo ke-Zevulun ben Dan*. Like Zevulun
ben Dan but not totally like it. כזבולון בן דן שלימדו אבי
אביו *ke-Zevulun ben Dan she-limmdo avi aviv*. No no the reason we're
talking about זבולון בן דן *Zevulun ben Dan* was not to talk
about the scope of the information that was taught. We were talking
about until how far do you have to teach meaning that the
obligation even extends from grandfathers to grandchildren the how far means generationally
how far we're going to talk about that but not how much
content. ולא כזבולון בן דן דאילו התם מקרא mikra, משנה mishna, ותלמוד
הלכות ואגדות *ve-lo ke-Zevulun ben Dan de-illu hatam Mikra Mishnah ve-Talmud Halachos
ve-aggados*. There was everything. דאילו הכא מקרא Mikra לבד *de-illu
hacha Mikra levad*. Here it's enough to teach him just Torah.
Meaning your grandchild just מקרא Mikra *mikra* not your son.
No no no because the previous ברייתא Braisah, *baraita* was about your
son. Now the זבולון בן דן *Zevulun ben Dan* was just an
example that the obligation extends to grandchildren. But the content according to
at least this approach in this ברייתא Braisah, *baraita* is only מקרא
Mikra, *mikra* which is again quite shocking. So you're telling me the
חיוב *chiyyuv* of תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah *Talmud Torah* is limited to
מקרא Mikra. *mikra*? So again it seems like what we're talking here
is the parental obligation of education. It's like to provide a primary
education that is not to be understood as the obligation an individual
has in terms of their own תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah. *Talmud Torah*
which is like vast right you're supposed to try to learn as
much learn everything. What, you're telling me the חיוב of תלמוד תורה
Talmud Torah. is limited to מקרא? Mikra, So again, it seems like
what we're talking about here is the parental obligation of education is
like providing primary education. That is not to be understood as the
obligation an individual has in terms of their own תלמוד תורה, Talmud
Torah. which is like vast, right? You're supposed to try to learn
as much and exactly what the parameters are. Is it just קריאת
שמע Krias Shema שחרית Shacharis and ערבית? Arvis? Is it just learning
a little bit every day? Am I supposed to master the entire,
you know, corpus? But certainly my own obligation of תלמוד תורה Torah
is obviously clearly generally understood as independent of my father's obligation to
teach me and much larger. So when the ברייתא said before, if
the father doesn't teach the son, the son has to teach himself,
presumably there we were talking about a primary education. The obligation on
primary education is father to son, but if he didn't provide it,
the son provides it himself. But presumably the larger obligation of תלמוד
תורה Torah is presumably independent. Although again, it didn't exactly fit the
stories before. It is a complicated thing that the גמרא Gemara doesn't
exactly figure out how all the pieces fit together in the puzzle.
Yes, Charlie.
At the time this was written, the only part of this rule
written down was מקרא. Okay. All the rest of it would have
been quite difficult.
Why? That was an oral tradition. Why did you need something? It's
only you that is so much linked to a written culture that
you think it's difficult to teach things if they're not written down.
Well also, if the father had gone to the ישיבה. yeshiva.
Oh well that's true, the fact that if the father was not
knowledgeable, then he wouldn't have the wherewithal. Oh that's an interesting point.
So you're saying maybe the reason to limit the father's obligation to
מקרא is not just that it's an obligation fundamentally about like primary
education, but also it's accessible to everybody. That's a very interesting thought.
Right, because anything beyond מקרא, you yourself would have to have a
good education to have that knowledge because it would not be written.
That's an interesting thought. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like
this. ואבי אביו מי מיחייב? Ve-avi aviv mi mechayev? Is the grandfather
really obligated? והתניא, Ve-hatanya, we learned in the ברייתא, ולמדתם אותם את
בניכם, Ve-limadetem osam es beneichem, you shall teach your sons, ולא בני
בניכם, Ve-lo benei beneichem, and not your grandsons. ומה אני מקיים והודעתם
לבניך ולבני בניך? U-mah ani mekayem Ve-hodasom le-vanecha u-le-venei vanecha? You shall
teach your children and your children's children, or your sons and your
sons' sons, the day you stood at הר סיני, Har Sinai, לומר
לך, Lomar lecha, to tell you שכל המלמד את בנו תורה, She-kol
ha-melamed es beno Torah, if you teach your son תורה, Torah, מעלה
עליו הכתוב כאילו למדו לו ולבנו ולבן בנו עד סוף כל הדורות.
Maaleh alav ha-kasuv ke-ilu limdo lo u-le-veno u-le-ven beno ad sof kol
ha-doros. So obviously education has this tremendous ripple effect. If you raise
your sons and make them תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim or at least
give them a good strong תורה Torah. education, then they'll pass that
down to their kids and their kids to their kids and it's
like you've taught all future generations תורה. Torah. Right? Very powerful idea.
So that's והודעתם לבניך ולבני בניך. Ve-hodasom le-vanecha u-le-venei vanecha. But your
obligation is only to your son, but it will translate into future
generations. Okay. הוא דאמר כי האי תנא. Hu de-amar ki hai tanna.
He holds like the other תנא. tanna. דתניא, De-tanya, we learned in
the ברייתא, ולמדתם אותם את בניכם, Ve-limadetem osam es beneichem, אין לי
אלא
בניכם, Ein li ela beneichem, I only know your sons. בני בניכם
מנין? Benei beneichem minayin? How do I know your grandsons? תלמוד לומר,
Talmud lomar, והודעתם לבניך ולבני בניך. Ve-hodasom le-vanecha u-le-venei vanecha. The other
פסוק, pasuk. you shall inform your sons and your sons' sons. אם
כן מה תלמוד לומר בניכם? Im ken mah talmud lomar beneichem? So
why does the first verse say just your sons? בניכם ולא בנותיכם.
Beneichem ve-lo benoseichem. Oh, like we said yesterday. Grandsons are included, daughters
are
excluded. Okay. אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי. Amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi.
כל המלמד את בן בנו תורה, Kol ha-melamed es ben beno Torah,
anybody who teaches his grandson תורה, Torah. מעלה עליו הכתוב כאילו קיבלה
מהר סיני, Maaleh alav ha-kasuv ke-ilu kiblah mi-Har Sinai, the תורה Torah,
treats him like he received it from הר סיני. Har Sinai. שנאמר,
She-ne'emar, והודעתם לבניך ולבני בניך, Ve-hodasom le-vanecha u-le-venei vanecha, you shall inform
your sons and grandsons, וסמיך ליה, u-samich lei, יום אשר עמדת לפני
ה' אלוהיך בחורב, Yom asher amadta lifnei Hashem Elokecha be-Chorev, the day
you stood at הר סיני. Har Sinai. Now it's interesting, you would
have thought the he... so the he... well okay, so obviously you
would think like it's the grand... I mean the grammar is the
he is the teacher, the grandfather. But the logic you would say
it's the grandson. If I, the grandson, am receiving it from my
grandfather, it's reaching back to
past generations—thank you—and it models for me this unbroken chain. But I
wonder if you could say the same about the grandfather. If I
see it as my responsibility to pass it down further down in
the chain, then that connects also makes me see that I'm part
of an unbroken
chain that reached all the way back.
Well, because my son is just like a direct obligation. I do
a lot of things for my kids. I raise my kids. I
give them an education. Right. I marry them off. But if I
teach my grandchildren, that shows that the obligation is one that goes
throughout generations and the passing down of תורה Torah. is a process
that continues through generations, so it also positions me that way vis-a-vis
prior generations. I think it's possible to read it that way.
This most length that you would probably go. Right, so it establishes
that idea even more strongly.
Yeah, after that you're going to...
you'll probably be dead. Right. So it means you don't really get
to write them something or some other people. Right. It's more personal.
Exactly.
Okay, so now the גמרא gemara. continues. רבי חייא בר אבא אשכחיה
לרבי יהושע בן לוי דשדי דיסנא ארישיה וקא ממטי ליה לינוקא לבי
כנישתא. Rabbi Chiya bar Abba ashcachei le-Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi de-shadi disna
a-reishei ve-ka mamti lei le-yanuka le-vei knishta. So רבי חייא בר אבא
Rabbi Chiya bar Abba found רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi Yehoshua ben
Levi that he had like a handkerchief on his head. He didn't
put the proper סודרא. sudara. Remember the סודרא sudara from before? Picking
up on that theme. So a good, you know, חשוב chashuv a
רב Rav doesn't go out from the house without a nice, you
know, turban on his head. But he would just threw a שמטה
shmata on his head. In order when it was time to take
his kid to school. Okay and where was it and he took
the kid לבי כנישתא lebei kenishta to the to the to the
שול shul where they had like חדר. cheder. אמרו ליה מאי כולי
האי? amru lei mai kulei hai? So people said to him, what
is this? Why'd you run out of your house with just throwing
a שמאטע shmatte on your head? You didn't put on a proper
headdress. אמר להו מי זוטר מאי דכתיב? amar lehu mi zutar mai
deksiv? Is it trivial what's meant in what the פסוק pasuk, says?
והודעתם לבניך? vehodatam livanecha? You shall inform your children. וסמיך ליה יום
אשר עמדת לפני ה' אלקיך בחורב, usamich lei yom asher amadta lifnei
Hashem Elokecha bechorev, the day you stood before Hashem at הר סיני.
Har Sinai. Meaning at הר סיני. Har Sinai. No, well, meaning that
I cannot trivialize, oh, you know, so what, so your kid's a
little late to חדר, cheder, you know? Or, you know, or maybe
let the mother take him. No. This is, you know, even teaching
the basic primary education providing your kids is part of being part
of this tradition that goes down to הר סיני, Har Sinai, receiving
it from the previous generation, passing it on to the next. So
I'm going to rush to make sure that I'm going to take
care of it and get my kid to school on time. Which
by the way is interesting, right? Because again, I wonder if one
wonders if it's playing off on the handkerchief on the head that
wasn't on the head before because of the guy who was maybe
like, you know, learning תורה, Torah. not getting married, and that was
the בבלי's Bavli approach, like get married first. And here's the guy,
it's רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi which is ארץ
ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, right? And he actually is taking care of his
parental obligations, you know, and not being so careful about the handkerchief
on his head as it were. So it seems like it might
be a play off on that. Yeah. Does he have anything else
to say about this סודר sudar on the head? In other words,
this is a sign of being a רב or a חכם? chacham?
Is it a sign of being married? It seems like it's both.
It seems like it's both. Yeah, yes. It seems like it's both.
You know, I don't know if it was a different type of
a headwear or whatever, but yes, it does seem it's a certain
status-wise, both of a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham and of a married
man. Okay. Now the גמרא Gemara continues. אמר רב ספרא משום רבי
יהושע בן חנניה. amar Rav Safra mishum Rabbi Yehoshua ben Chananya. What?
I think you... I'm sorry. Thank you, thank you. מכאן ואילך mikan
va'eilach from that point on, רבי חייא בר אבא Rabbi Chiya bar
Abba who was questioning the behavior of רבי יהושע בן לוי, Rabbi
Yehoshua ben Levi, לא טעים אומצא lo ta'im umtza he would not
even eat like a little bit of meat in the morning. Interesting,
meat in the morning, you know, I always grew up, that's not
something Jews do. That, you know, what, bacon in the morning? Whatever.
Anyway, he wouldn't have meat in the morning עד דמקרי לינוקא ad
demakri liyenuka until he
would teach a child, let's not say for his child, but anyway,
some פסוקים pesukim again we're at basic מקרא, okay, ומוספי umosefei not
only have him
חוזר chozer what he learned the previous day and do a little
extra teaching, you know, have the kid read over the פסוקים pesukim
that they learned yesterday and teach him one more פסוק. pasuk So
he would've, you know, make sure to first do it's a, you
know, to first do this as a primary obligation before he did
anything else. רבה בר רב הונא לא
טעים אומצא עד דמייתי לינוקא
לבי מדרשא.
Rabba bar Rav Huna lo ta'im umtza ad demaiti
liyenuka lebei midrasha.
He wouldn't have a little bit to eat until he brought the
kid to the בית מדרש. beis medrash. Okay. אמר רב ספרא משום
רבי יהושע בן חנניה. amar Rav Safra mishum Rabbi Yehoshua ben Chananya.
מאי דכתיב? mai deksiv? What's meant by the verse ושננתם לבניך? veshinnantam
livanecha? You shall articulate them. The word ושננתם veshinnantam like, or you
know, you shall repeat them, articulate them to your children, to your
sons. אל תקרי ושננתם אלא ושלשתם. al tikri veshinnantam ela veshillashtam. Okay,
so רש"י says it could've said ו... vav what does רש"י say
it could've said? ושניתם. veshanitem. So somehow ושננתם, veshinnantam, the double נ
nun is telling you like the word שני sheni but now added
to the word more than two, three times. לעולם ישלש אדם שנותיו.
le'olam yeshalesh adam shenotav. And maybe the word שנה shana here also.
A person should divide his years into three. שליש במקרא שליש במשנה
ושליש בתלמוד shlish bemikra shlish bemishna ushlish betalmud a third of your
life devoted to to פסוקים, pesukim, a third to משנה, mishna a
third to גמרא. gemara, So the גמרא Gemara says מי יודע כמה
חיי? mi yodea kama chayei? How do you know how long you're
going to live that you can divide your life that way? לא
צריכא ליומי. lo tzricha leyomei. No, divide your day that way. Okay,
so which presumably means, which could mean divide every day three, you
know, three hours to this, three hours to that, three hours, or
רש"י says it means like within the week, you know, two days
a week for מקרא, two days for משנה, Mishna. two days for
גמרא, gemara. שבת Shabbos you take off or something, or you do
חזרה. chazara. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara. says לפיכך נקראו. lefikach nikre'u.
Now, the next point is a different point. Now, if you take
a look, תוספות Tosafot says the following. Look at תוספות. Tosafot. לא
צריכא ליומי, lo tzricha leyomei, פירש בקונטרס ימי השבוע, peireish bekuntres yemei
hashavua, כלומר שני ימים מקרא שני ימים משנה שני ימים גמרא. klomar
shenei yamim mikra shenei yamim mishna shenei yamim gemara. ולא נהירא דאם
כן אכתי הוי מצי למיפרך מי יודע כמה חיי. velo nehira de'im
kein achti havei matzi lemifrach mi yodea kama chayei. How do you
know, maybe you'll die in the middle of a week and you
won't have been יוצא yotzei that last week having divided it into
three. נו. nu. Anyway, תוספות Tosafot says ונראה לפרש שבכל יום ויום
עצמו ישלש. venireh lefareish shebechol yom vayom atzmo yeshalesh. Every day, a
third this, a third that. על כן תיקן בסדר רב עמרם גאון
כמו שאנו נוהגים בכל יום קודם פסוקי דזמרא לומר מקרא משנה וגמרא.
al kein tikein beseder Rav Amram Gaon kemo she'anu nohagim bechol yom
kodem pesukei dezimra lomar mikra mishna ugemara. Some people have this, right?
That in the learning before פסוקי דזמרא, pesukei dezimra, you know, some
people do like a little bit of פרשה parsha and a little
משנה Mishna, and a little line of גמרא. Gemara. So every day
you're learning. It's not exactly dividing a third of the day, but
depending if you're working all day maybe it's dividing the amount of
available time you have. I mean it's... what? Just dividing every day.
I mean תוספות Tosafot doesn't answer all the questions. Maybe you'll die
in the mid- I know, at a certain point you can't be
too-
you gotta you know you can't be over- but... I guess he
feels he's as precise as he can be. Wait, let me just
finish. רבנו תם פירוש אנו סומכין. Rabbeinu Tam pirush anu somchin. So,
you know, does that really satisfy? That's like a pro-forma little וויץ.
vitz. That's not really dividing your day. And we all know that
the basic focus of learning, maybe after somebody was a kid, you
know, and got their primary education, the basic focus of learning was
always גמרא. Gemara? So how do you justify that? So תוספות Tosafot
says רבנו תם פירוש אנו סומכין אהא דאמרינן בסנהדרין בבבל, Rabbeinu Tam
pirush anu somchin aha de'amrinan beSanhedrin beVavel, it's called the Babylonian Talmud,
why? בלולה belulah because it's mixed together with so many different things.
במקרא במשנה ובגמרא. beMikra, beMishna, ubeGemara. דגמרא
בבל בלולה מכולם. deGemara Bavel belulah mikulam. Oh, you learn the בבלי
Bavli and that gets you מקרא and משנה. Mishna, You learn a
משנה, Mishna, you quote some ברייתות, beraitot, every now and then you
quote a פסוק, pasuk like somebody says, oh yeah, it's a פסוק
pasuk in בבא בתרא Bava Batra somewhere. So that's how you get,
that's how you get it all. So that's how you're יוצא yotzei
this גמרא. Gemara Now the רמב"ם Rambam in הלכות תלמוד תורה Hilchot
Talmud Torah has a very interesting רמב"ם. Rambam. The רמב"ם Rambam says
the following. This tended to be, and I don't remember off the
top of my head all the specifics of it, but this actually
was a big issue of obviously an educational issue that's throughout the
ages. You know, A, just how do you try to satisfy this
structure of the גמרא? Gemara Number one. And number two, how do
you interpret it, right? And different educational philosophies. So the רמב"ם Rambam
anyway says פרק א הלכה הלכות תלמוד תורה הלכה יא. perek aleph
halacha Hilchot Talmud Torah halacha yud-aleph. The רמב"ם Rambam says like this,
וחייב
לשלש את זמן לימודו. vechayav leshalesh et zman limudo. You have to
divide it into thirds. שליש בתורה שבכתב ושליש בתורה שבעל פה ושליש
יבין וישכיל אחרית דבר מראשיתו. shlish baTorah shebikhtav veshlish baTorah shebe'al peh
veshlish yavin veyaskil acharit davar mereshito. So the תורה שבעל פה Torah
shebe'al peh. is apparently the received traditions and that's משנה, Mishna? according
to משנה, Mishna, it's not just תנאי Tannaitic material, it's any part
of the received traditions. And the last third is your own analysis,
okay. ויוציא דבר מדבר וידמה דבר לדבר ויבין במידות שהתורה נדרשת בהן
veyotzi davar midavar veyidmeh davar ledavar veyavin bemidot shehaTorah nidreshet bahen etc.
etc. עניין זה נקרא גמרא. inyan zeh nikra Gemara. כיצד, keitzad, how,
what does this mean to divide your day into thirds? היה בעל
אומנות, hayah ba'al omanut, let's say you had a, you had a
trade. שהיה עוסק במלאכתו שלוש שעות ביום. shehayah osek bimlakhto shalosh sha'ot
bayom. And you spend three hours a day at your trade, okay.
ותורה תשע, veTorah tesha, so you have nine hours a day left
for learning תורה. Torah אותן התשע קורא בשלוש מהן בתורה שבכתב ובשלוש
בתורה שבעל פה ובשלוש אחרות מתבונן בדעתו להבין דבר דבר otan hatesha
korei beshalosh mehen baTorah shebikhtav uveshalosh baTorah shebe'al peh uveshalosh acherot mitbonen
beda'ato lehavin davar davar etc. etc. etc. Then the רמב"ם Rambam says
like this. Now, that's so taking the גמרא Gemara. very literally. But
really? So my whole life I'm supposed to spend a third of
my day in מקרא and a third in משנה? So then the
רמב"ם Rambam modifies the גמרא Gemara, in the following way. And the
רמב"ם Rambam says במה דברים אמורים בתחילת תלמודו של אדם. bameh devarim
amurim betchilat talmudo shel adam. That's when you are doing your primary
education, okay, when you're just getting started. Although here if you're working,
you know, what I mean, where were you educated by your father
as a kid? But anyway, when you're still establishing your basic knowledge
base and your skills, okay. אבל כשיגדיל בחכמה ולא יצטרך לא ללמוד
תורה שבכתב ולא לעסוק תמיד בתורה שבעל פה. aval kesheyagdil bechochmah velo
yitzaterech lo lilmod Torah shebikhtav velo la'asok tamid baTorah shebe'al peh. Once
you know תנ"ך and once you know the
traditions, okay. יקרא בעתים מזומנים תורה שבכתב ודברי השמועה כדי שלא ישכח
דבר מדברי דיני תורה. yikra be'ittim mezumanim Torah shebikhtav vedivrei hashemu'ah kedei
shelo yishkach davar midivrei dinei Torah. So occasionally you review it, you
know, you review the stuff that you already know, the תורה שבכתב
Torah shebikhtav and תורה שבעל פה. torah sheba'al peh. ויפנה כל ימיו
לגמרא בלבד. veyifneh kol yamav leGemara bilvad. But all of your real
emphasis goes in learning גמרא. Gemara, לפי רוחב שיש בלבו ויישוב דעתו.
lefi rochav sheyesh belibo veyishuv da'ato. So in the end it becomes
very similar to תוספות. Tosafot. You spend all your time learning גמרא,
Gemara. which is basically the ethos of the גמרא, Gemara right? But
the רמב"ם Rambam satisfies the idea of a third by putting that
towards when you're still growing and developing your skills and so on.
Yes, Rabbi Idog.
I thought I heard how to get the third. ושננתם, veshinantam, the
first learning is
שינון. shinun.
So it's like there are three נs. nun Oh, that's interesting. Okay,
יישר כוח. yashar koach. Alright, back to the גמרא.
Gemara רמב"ם Rambam didn't work only three hours.
Right, well that's always so ironic because everybody quotes רמב"ם, Rambam, oh
you see the רמב"ם Rambam thinks that even if you have a
פרנסה parnassah you should only work three hours a day. If you
read the רמב"ם's Rambam letter that he writes towards, you know, it
was true, it was towards the end of his life, but when
he was as a doctor and he was basically saying exactly, he
speaks about his normal day, he didn't have like, he didn't have
time to say קריאת שמע Kri'at Shema almost, you know. The only
time he says I get to learn is like for an hour
on שבת, Shabbat, you know. So anyway. Alright, so anyway, the גמרא
Gemara says like this. Alright, so okay. Now
the לפיכך lefikach is a very strange לפיכך lefikach because it doesn't
seem to be connected at all to the theme or something of
the previous teaching. And רש"י says this is a מילתא אחריתי. milta
achrita. Anyway, לפיכך נקראו ראשונים סופרים. lefikach nikre'u rishonim sofrim. The,
the early sages were called סופרים sofrim שהיו סופרים כל אותיות שבתורה.
shehayu sofrim kol otiyot shebaTorah.
They would count all of the letters in the תורה. Torah. Maybe
because we're dealing with a third and dividing, I don't know where
what the link is here. Anyway, שהיו אומרים ו דגחון חצין של
אותיות של ספר תורה. shehayu omerim vav degechon chatzyan shel otiyot shel
sefer Torah.
The big ו vav in כל הולך על גחון kol holekh al
gachon is half the letters in the ספר תורה. sefer Torah. דרש
דרש חצין של תיבות. darosh darash chatzyan shel teivot. When it says
את שעיר החטאת, et se'ir hachatat, we just had this דרש דרש
משה, darosh darash Moshe, that's exactly half of the words in the
תורה. Torah והתגלח. vehitgalach. which is also just we just had, okay,
so is והתגלח vehisgalach של פסוקים. shel psukim.
That's half of the פסוקים. psukim. Okay, יכרסמנה חזיר מיער, ycharsmena chazir
miyaar,
now this פסוק pasuk in תהלים Tehillim that a the the whatever
the the pig will you know
consume it like they'll be consumed like a pig in the in
the in the forest, עין דיער, ayin de'yaar, the עין ayin of
יער yaar חצין של תהלים chetzyan shel Tehillim is half of תהלים
Tehillim in letters. והוא רחום יכפר עון vehu rachum yechapeir avon and
that פסוק pasuk in תהלים Tehillim חציו דפסוקים chetzyo d'psukim is half
of the פסוקים psukim in תהלים. Tehillim. Now the problem with so
many of these is that it doesn't work. Okay? That based on
our countings and whatever it doesn't work. What?
Do any of them work?
I don't know. Some of them are very off. So בעי רב
יוסף, baei Rav Yosef, so רב יוסף Rav Yosef asks ו דגחון
vav degachon מהאי גיסא או מהאי גיסא? mehai gisa o mehai gisa?
Is the ו vav which half of the—maybe it's the exact middle?
Maybe there's an odd number of letters? But anyway is it the
exact middle letter or which side of the divide is it on?
אמר ליה amar lei אייתי ספר תורה ואמנינהו, ayisi sefer torah v'imninhu,
why don't let's get a ספר תורה sefer torah and count the
letters? So רב says no, מי לא אמר רבה בר בר חנה
לא זזו משם עד שהביאו ספר תורה ומנאום? mi lo amar Rabbah
bar bar Chanah lo zazu misham ad sheheviu sefer torah u'mnaum? Isn't
there another case where they had a question and they got out
the ספר תורה sefer torah and counted the letters? רש״י Rashi says
we don't know what that other case was.
So what's the question?
So why do you have to ask what the ו vav is?
Let's just—let's just do it, let's figure it out. אמר ליה no,
אינהו בקיאי בחסירות ויתירות. inhu bki'ei b'chaseros v'yesiros. In the earlier generations
they knew whether the words were written with whole or lacking, like
was אהרן Aharon written with a ו vav, or without a ו,
you know? So that and therefore they had a precise letters of
the ספר תורה. sefer torah. אנן לא בקיאינן. anan lo bki'inan. We
don't—our ספר תורה sefer torah might not be exactly precise in חסירות
ויתירות. chaseros v'yesiros. So there goes all the Bible codes because the
גמרא Gemara. says here that even in the time of the אמוראים
Amoraim they didn't have a precise knowledge of exactly what every letter
was. Okay? And again but even with that it's not enough clear
you know it was the period of the—it was the בן אשר
Ben Asher family which was what fifth century, sixth century?
Something
right that they were the ones that they were the you know
the בעלי המסורה baalei hamesorah Masoretes that they really did count every
single letter and cataloged it so that that kept a very fixed
text of the תורה, Torah you know? Because they cataloged exactly everything,
but that was only starting like the sixth century or something like
that. So you know after this. So at this stage they were
still a lot—there were still a lot of variants, but nevertheless a
lot of these numbers are very off. So I don't know how
it's really explained how off they got.
Is it another family too? There was like several Masoretes?
Oh were there?
Okay. So, by the way, תוספות Tosafot has an interesting תוספות Tosafot
about סופרים. soferim. If you look at תוספות Tosafot נקראו סופרים nikre'u
soferim because like the early generations right we say דברי סופרים, divrei
soferim, right? It's a way of referring to the very early generations
of rabbis. So this גמרא Gemara says because they would be counting
the words of the תורה. Torah, But תוספות Tosafot has another interesting
פשט pshat comment on this. תוספות Tosafot says פירוש בקונטרס כדכתיב ומשפחות
סופרים יושבי יעבץ peirush bakontres kedichtiv umishpachos soferim yoshvei Yabetz
referring to the פסוק pasuk about you know that refers to a
family of scribes and that's the early sort of early right pre-rabbinic
sort of generation. ובירושלמי מפרש uvirushalmi mefareish
that סופרים soferim was also ascribed to the early rabbis שהשיאו כל
התורה כולה מספרות she'his'iu kol hatorah kulah misparos that they assigned numbers
to things. What does that mean? Not to פסוקים. psukim. תורה שבעל
פה. torah sheba'al peh כגון אבות מלאכות ארבעים חסר אחת, avos melachos
arbaim chaser achas, ארבעה אבות נזיקין, arba'ah avos nezikin, כיוצא בהן האשה
נקנית בשלוש דרכים, kiyotzei bahen ha'isha nikneis b'shalosh drachim, right the idea
of trying to organize information by clearly numbering how many ways this
is done, how many things, right, yeah but yeah that's different but
this is like you know cataloging the—the sort of the law. Okay
so it's a nice way of organizing information. Interesting also like when
does you know those משניות of numbers, saying that that came at
an early stage in terms of organizing תורה Torah שבעל פה information.
What's
יעבץ? Yabetz? Well that's—I mean that's—it's interpreted—yeah, it's interpreted to mean I
think descendants of יתרו Yisro and so on. That's how חז״ל Chazal
interpreted it. Anyway back to the גמרא. Gemara The גמרא Gemara says
like
this. בעי רב יוסף, baei Rav Yosef, רב יוסף Rav Yosef asks
six lines from the
bottom. והתגלח vehisgalach של פסוקים shel psukim מהאי גיסא או מהאי גיסא?
mehai gisa o mehai gisa? Which side of the divide is it
on? And here you can't say you could say we might not
know extra letters but presumably we know how to divide the פסוקים.
psukim. So why don't let's—you know—so אמר ליה אביי פסוקי מי לא
ליתו ולמנינהו? amar lei Abaye psukei mi lo leisu u'lmininhu? So yeah
there we should be able to find an answer, let's count פסוקים
psukim and presumably we know where the פסוקים psukim are divided. So
the גמרא Gemara says בפסוקי נמי לא בקיאינן. bpsukei nami lo bki'inan.
No, we might not know exactly where the פסוקים psukim are divided.
דכי אתא רב אחא בר אדא אמרי במערבא פסקי ליה להאי קרא
לתלתא פסוקי. d'ki ata Rav Acha bar Adda amri b'maarava paski lei
l'hai kra l'tlasa psukei. A פסוק pasuk we have as one פסוק
pasuk. in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael they divide it into three פסוקים.
psukim. What is it? ויאמר ה׳ אל משה הנה אנכי בא אליך
בעב הענן. vayomer Hashem el Moshe hinei anochi ba eilecha b'av he'anan.
So presumably you could put an end of a פסוק pasuk there.
בעבור ישמע העם בדברי עמך וגם בך יאמינו לעולם ba'avur yishma ha'am
b'dabri imcha v'gam becha ya'aminu l'olam is presumably another one. Although בעבור
ישמע ba'avur yishma is an interesting way to start a פסוק. pasuk
ויגד משה את דברי העם אל ה׳. vayageid Moshe es divrei ha'am
el Hashem. So they divide that into three פסוקים. psukim. Okay, so
yeah there could be a debate also about how to count the
פסוקים. psukim. Okay. תנו רבנן. tanu rabanan. חמשת אלפים ושמונה מאות ושמונים
ושמונה פסוקים הוו פסוקי ספר תורה. chameshes alapim u'shmoneh meios u'shmonim u'shmoneh
psukim havu psukei sefer torah.
5,888 are the פסוקים psukim of the ספר תורה. Sefer Torah. Of
course, in our counting it's 5,400 and I mean 5,845.
So we're off by about 40 or so. Okay. יתר עליו תהלים.
yeter alav Tehillim. תהלים Tehillim is more פסוקים. psukim. שמונה חסר? shmonah
chasar? No, שמונה. shmonah. Eight more פסוקים. psukim. Of course, תוספות Tosafot
says, if you look at this little תוספות Tosafot higher up on
the דף daf in the bracket, יתר עליו תהלים שמונה, yeter alav
Tehillim shmonah, eight more פסוקים psukim than in the תורה. Torah, תוספות
Tosafot says תימה דעל כרחך בחומש יש יותר דאפילו הוו פסוקי תהלים
מג' תיבות בלחוד. teima de-al korchacha be-Chumash yesh yoter de-afillu havu psukei
Tehillim mi-gimmel teivot be-lachud. Even if you took all the words of
the תהלים Tehillim and made a פסוק out of every three words,
okay, he says, אינו כל כך כמו שיש בחומש. eino kol kach
kemo she-yesh be-Chumash. You would not have as many פסוקים psukim as
in the חומש. Chumash. So what does the גמרא Gemara mean that
פסוקים psukim has eight more, תהלים Tehillim has eight more פסוקים psukim
than the חומש? Chumash? Okay. Anyway, חסר ממנו דברי הימים. chasar mimeno
Divrei HaYamim. I know, דברי הימים Divrei HaYamim has eight fewer than
the חומש, Chumash, שמונה. shmonah. Okay. And I just have to tell
you one more just really funny story, which is
about this דרש מכאן ודרש מכאן. darosh mikan ve-darosh mikan. So that
פסוק comes up in שמיני. Shemini. And this year, you know, שמיני
Shemini we're earlier in the פרשיות parshiyot than we would normally be
in the year, but often שמיני Shemini is right around פסח. Pesach.
So somebody told me that he was once in שול, shul, which
was like, you know, it was the שבת חול המועד פסח. Shabbat
Chol HaMoed Pesach. No, it was
שבת מוצאי פסח, Shabbat Motzei Pesach, you know, at the end of
it, it was פרשת שמיני, Parashat Shemini, right? It was after like
this whole big יום טוב Yom Tov of פסח, Pesach, three day
יום טוב Yom Tov at the end, right? Everybody was like, you
know, exhausted out of שול. shul. Nobody was, nobody wanted to hear
like the rabbi's sermon, you know, by the שבת, Shabbat, let's say,
whatever. Anyway, so it's פרשת שמיני. Parashat Shemini. So the rabbi gets
up and he tells the joke. You know the joke about the
חסידים Chassidim that are comparing how great their rabbi is? You know,
my rabbi is so great, he was walking home one day and
it was, and it was like raining and he said, וואסער אהין
וואסער אהער, vasser ahin vasser aher, and the water split and he
walked through dry. And the others say, "Well, my rabbi, he was
walking, you know, he came to a river. He said, וואסער אהין
וואסער אהער vasser ahin vasser aher and he walked through the mountains."
He says, "Ah, that's nothing. My rabbi is so great. One day
he was walking and it was שבת Shabbat and he found on
the ground, he saw a 20 dollar bill. $20! So what did
he do? He said, שבת אהין שבת אהער Shabbat ahin Shabbat aher
and he picked up the 20 dollars." So everybody cracks up. So
then the rabbi says, "This week's פרשה parasha we read, את שעיר
החטאת דרש דרש משה והנה שרף. et se'ir hachatat darosh darosh Moshe
vehineh soraf. And the מסורה Masorah teaches
us חצי התורה במילים, chatzi ha-Torah be-milim, it's half the Torah in
the words. דרש מכאן ודרש מכאן. darosh mikan ve-darosh mikan. דרשה אהין
דרשה אהער, drasha ahin drasha aher, מוסף Musaf starts on page 360."
So they knew
this context, though they're always in that. All right.
So now the גמרא Gemara. says like this. Okay.
תנו רבנן: Tanu Rabbanan: ושננתם. ve-shinnantam. Okay.
ושננתם לבניך. ve-shinnantam le-vanecha. You shall ושננתם לבניך, ve-shinnantam le-vanecha, you shall
teach them, you shall repeat them, you shall articulate them. So here
it reads it as articulate. שיהיו דברי תורה מחודדים בפיך. she-yehyu divrei
Torah me-chuddadim be-ficha. The words of תורה Torah, should be sharp, like
שנון shinnun is like sharp, right? To, they should be sharp in
your mouth. שאם ישאל לך אדם דבר אל תגמגם ותאמר לו. she-im
yishal lecha adam davar al tegagaym ve-tomar lo. If somebody asks you
something, don't hesitate and stumble over it, אלא אמור לו מיד. ella
emor lo miyad. They should be so accessible to you that you
should have the answers at the tip of your tongue. שנאמר, she-ne'emar,
that's how you have to learn תורה. Torah, שנאמר אמר לחכמה אחותי
את. she-ne'emar emor la-chochmah achoti at. Say to חכמה, chochmah, you are
my sister. You should know it as well as you know your
sister, or another דרשה, drasha, as well as you know your sister
is forbidden to you. Okay. ואומר קשרם על אצבעותיך כתבם על לוח
לבך. ve-omer koshrem al etzbe'otecha katvem al lu'ach libbecha. Tie them on
your fingers, write them on, you know, on the chambers of your
heart. They should be on, you know, they should be completely internalized
and, you know, in your blood. ואומר כחצים ביד גיבור כן בני
הנעורים. ve-omer ke-chitzim be-yad gibbor ken bnei ha-ne'urim. Like arrows, again the
idea of sharpness, right, in the hands of the hero of the,
whatever, the warrior. כן בני הנעורים, ken bnei ha-ne'urim, so are the
sons of the youth. רש"י says it means that the, like your
learning is called your children. Also maybe the learning that you do
when you're young is stuff that you really remember is very sharp.
ואומר חצי גיבור שנונים. ve-omer chitzey gibbor shnunim. The arrows of the,
of the, of what's again, not the hero, what's the word for
גיבור? gibbor? Of the courageous, of the warrior are sharp. ואומר חציך
שנונים עמים תחתיך יפלו. ve-omer chitzeycha shnunim ammim tachteycha yippolu. Your arrows
are sharp, nations will fall below you. ואומר אשרי הגבר אשר מילא
את אשפתו מהם. ve-omer ashrei ha-gever asher millei et aspato me-hem. Praised
is the man that fills his quiver with these arrows, that you
know all of your תורה Torah and, you know, your knowledge, you
know you have all this תורה Torah under your belt and it's
sharp. לא יבשו כי ידברו את אויבים בשער. lo yevoshu ki yedabberu
et oyvim ba-sha'ar. You will not be embarrassed when you speak with
the enemies in the gate, like when you talk תורה, Torah you
know, and argue תורה Torah with people. Now what does it mean
enemies? מאי את אויבים בשער? mai et oyvim ba-sha'ar? אמר רבי חייא
בר אבא: Amar Rabbi Chiyya bar Abba: אפילו האב ובנו הרב ותלמידו.
afillu ha-av u-vno ha-rav ve-talmido. even father and son, the rabbi and
student, שעוסקים בתורה בשער אחד, she-oskim ba-Torah be-sha'ar echad, which normally you
have to show deference to your master and to your father and
everything, nevertheless, when you're עוסקים בתורה בשער אחד, oskim ba-Torah be-sha'ar echad,
when they're in these gates of תורה, Torah, you know, they're in
the one house and arguing in תורה, Torah נעשים אויבים זה לזה.
na'asim oyvim zeh la-zeh. They can, they're like, they becomes enemies. Everybody
is fighting for, you know, arguing and yelling. You've ever been in
a loud בית מדרש? Beit Midrash? And you know, how could you
say... Doesn't make any sense and so on. Okay, hopefully it's not
personal; it's about their ideas. Anyway, ואינם זזים משם, v'aynam zazim misham,
but don't think that that's how it ends, because at the end
of all, you know, it's all לשם שמים l'shem shamayim and in
search of truth so they never, they don't leave and depart their
encounter עד שנעשים אוהבים זה לזה. ad shenasim ohavim zeh lazeh. In
the end they become, they love one another because they're all there
for the, to the sake of תלמוד תורה. Torah שנאמר Shene'emar את
והב בסופה, et vahev b'sufah, you know, it's ספר מלחמות ה', sefer
milchamot Hashem, the ספר sefer of the fights or you know the
wars of God. So Rashi says that when the wars of God
are over ספר sefer or over תורה, Torah you know, or over
what's in the ספרים sefarim and so on. So את והב בסופה.
et vahev b'sufah. אל תקרי בסופה אלא בסופה al tikrei b'sufah ela
b'sofah and והב vahev is written אהב. ahav. So אהבה, ahava, love,
comes at the end of that type of a war. So this
is quite interesting in a number of ways. Number one is is
the whole idea that, you know, well the primary one is that
the תורה Torah here is being, you know, this, this violent or
militaristic image around תלמוד תורה. Torah Daniel Boyarin wrote about this a
lot, about you know that normally study is like you know sort
of תורה Torah study or whatever that could sort of be seen
as a very non-masculine type of an activity, a very effeminate type
of a thing and that the rabbis make it extremely masculine, right?
They use all of this, you know, warrior imagery around it, you
know, and so going out and fighting and the warrior and so
on. It's interesting because we also just talked about choosing between תורה
Torah and marriage and he has another whole discussion about you know
תורה as the other woman, right? Sort of the relationship to תורה,
you know, and your love for תורה and taking you away. So
interesting sort of different metaphors around תלמוד תורה. The other interesting thing
of course is, notice how we've shifted from, oh, your basic obligation
is just to learn מקרא, right, you know, or just your father's
to teach you מקרא. And now of course we have, you know,
this idea of that you have to be ושננתם v'shinnantam to teach
you a completely different level of obligation, you know, that you have
to have all of this תורה under your belt and it has
to be sharp and it has to be accessible, right, and all
this thing obviously, you know, much more. And how about the fact
that the גמרא Gemara says that your right, that you're, you should
be dividing your days: מקרא, משנה, גמרא. Gemara Like what is that?
Is that a minimum and a maximum? Are those different types of
obligations, a primary, primary education obligation as opposed to an ongoing lifelong
learning? Not exactly clear how to sit these pieces all together. The
last thing I also have to say, maybe we'll try to read
a little bit more but anyway I just almost all my good
stories are related to these גמרות Gemaros anyway. I had a חברותא
chavrusa many years ago, you know, this גמרא Gemara. you know who
said, you know there's another גמרא that says right, אשר אנכי מצוך
היום, asher anochi m'tzavcha hayom, בכל יום יהיו בעיניך כחדשים. b'chol yom
yihyu b'einecha k'chadashim.
Every day you learn תורה it should be like something new and
exciting and so on. So I had a חברותא chavrusa said to
me: ושננתם לבניך, v'shinnantam l'vanecha, שיהיו מחודדים בפיך, sheyihyu mechudadim b'ficha, that
I'm not מקיים. m'kayem. בכל יום בעיניך כחדשים, b'chol yom b'einecha k'chadashim,
that I am מקיים. m'kayem.
So anyway. All right, so anyway, let's just read a little bit
more in the גמרא. תנו רבנן, Tanu rabanan, a little אגדתא aggadata
here. ושמתם, v'samtem,
right, this is the פסוקים psukim of קריאת שמע. Krias Shema. ושננתם
לבניך ודברת בם, v'shinnantam l'vanecha v'dibarta bam, ושמתם, v'samtem, right, לאות על
ידך. l'ot al yadecha. You shall place them as a sign. ושמתם,
v'samtem, a complete, what? וקשרתם לאות על ידך, ukshartam l'ot al yadecha,
thank you. ושמתם על מזוזות ביתך ובשעריך, v'samtem al mezuzot beitecha u'visharecha,
I'm sorry, right. Okay, sorry, what? ושמתם... v'samtem...
Oh what am I talking about? I'm sorry, thank you. ושמתם את
דברי אלה, v'samtem et dvarai eileh, אשר אנכי מצוך היום. asher anochi
m'tzavcha hayom.
Thank you, okay, anyway, סם תם. sam tam. So a, so a
complete healing or a complete potion or, um, so
it's actually like you know what would be a panacea, something that,
that is a full heal, that that works under all circumstances. That's
what the תורה is. נמשלה תורה כסם חיים. nimshla Torah k'sam chayim.
The תורה is like a potion of life. משל לאדם שהכה את
בנו מכה גדולה. mashal l'adam she'hikah et bno maka gdola.
A person, interesting משל, mashal, a person hit his son, right, with
a big smiting. והניח לו רטייה על מכתו v'hiniach lo rtiya al
makato and put a bandage on the wound. ואמר לו בני כל
זמן שרטייה זו על מכתך, v'amar lo bni kol zman she'rtiya zo
al makatecha, as long as this bandage is on your wound, אכול
מה שהנאתך ושתה מה שהנאתך, echol mah she'hanacha u'shtei mah she'hanacha,
eat whatever you want, drink whatever you want, all the stuff that's
supposed to be bad for wounds, don't worry, this bandage will counteract
them, is a panacea. ורחץ בין בחמין בין בצונן. v'rachatz bein b'chamim
bein b'tzonem. You don't have to worry how you're bathing, hot or
cold. ואין אתה מתיירא, v'ein ata mitya're, and you don't have to
worry about the effect. ואם אתה מעבירה, v'im ata ma'avirah, but if
you take it off, הרי היא מעלה נומי, harei hi ma'aleh numi,
then it's going to develop some type of an infection. כך הקדוש
ברוך הוא אמר להם לישראל. kach Hakadosh Baruch Hu amar lahem l'Yisrael.
God said to ישראל, Yisrael, בני, bni, בראתי יצר הרע, barati yetzer
hara, I guess that's the smiting. God the Father smote and He
created the bandage. So I created the יצר הרע, yetzer hara, that
can come and attack you, okay, ובראתי לו תורה תבלין, u'barati lo
Torah tavlin, but I've also created תורה which is the... The antidote
for the יצר הרע. yetzer hara. ואם אתם עוסקים בתורה אינכם נמסרים
בידו. ve-im atem oskim ba-Torah einchem nimsarim beyado.
If you're learning Torah, then that will, then that will prevent, that
will be the panacea, that will totally protect you from the influence
of the יצר הרע, yetzer hara, שנאמר, shene'emar, הלא אם תטיב שאת,
halo im teitiv se'eit,
if you do good, which is meant to be here, learn Torah,
Rashi says שאת se'eit means that you will conquer over the יצר
הרע, yetzer hara, you will be lifted over it. ואם אין אתם
עוסקים בתורה, ve-im ein atem oskim ba-Torah, but if you don't learn
Torah, אתם נמסרים בידו, atem nimsarim beyado, שנאמר, shene'emar, לפתח חטאת רבץ,
lapetach chatat roveitz,
but it's crouching there by the doorway. ולא עוד אלא שכל משאו
ומתנו בך, velo od ela shekol masao umatano bach, it's constantly, you
know, involved in you, its whole focus is on how to try
to attack you and developing schemes, the יצר הרע. yetzer hara. If
anybody ever read the book The Screwtape Letters by C.S. Lewis, it's
a great book. It's about, you know, Satan giving advice to a
little, a little imp, a little underling who's trying to seduce, you
know, a human being and trying to develop all the schemes and
how to work at seducing him. Anyway, it's constantly figuring out how
to scheme against you, שנאמר, shene'emar, ואליך תשוקתו, ve'eilecha teshukato, its desire
is towards you. ואם אתה רוצה אתה מושל בו, ve-im ata rotze
ata moshel bo, but you in the end can be victorious over
it, שנאמר, shene'emar, ואתה תמשול בו. ve'ata timshol bo. Okay, so we'll
pick up tomorrow with this issue about the challenge of the יצר
הרע yetzer hara and how the תורה can be the pure antidote
for the יצר הרע. yetzer hara.